<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hypocritical nation described in a sermon preached at St. Maries in Cambridge, upon a day of publick fasting : with an epistle prefixed by Mr. Samuel Jacombe.</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2023</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12629000</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12629000</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64705</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64705)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 726:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hypocritical nation described in a sermon preached at St. Maries in Cambridge, upon a day of publick fasting : with an epistle prefixed by Mr. Samuel Jacombe.</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
                  <author>Jacombe, Samuel, d. 1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Adoniram Byfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Simon Patrick by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zechariah VII, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64705:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64705:1"/>
            <p>THE Hypocritical Nation DESCRIBED, IN A SERMON PREACHED At St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> upon a day of Publick FASTING.</p>
            <p>With an Epiſtle prefixed by Mr <hi>Samuel Jacombe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Chryſoſt. Orat.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <q>Becauſe of unrighteous dealings, injuries, and riches got by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; the Kingdome is tranſlated from one people to another,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt. 10.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Adoniram Byfield,</hi> at the Bible in Popes-head Alley neer <hi>Lumbardſtreet.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64705:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64705:2"/>
            <head>READER</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well known, that an Hypocrite is an <hi>Artificial peice,</hi> a meer Cheat, a Stage-Player, every thing almoſt but what he ſeems to be, who makes Religion ſerve ſome private end, or thruſt himſelf into the company of Profeſſors, as the <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Deer</hi> doth into the midſt of the herd, becauſe he hopes for ſome outward ſafety: but the knife that gliſters well is quickly found to be what it is, <hi>all lead,</hi> by cutting ſomething <hi>hard</hi> with it, for it bends e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way: Follow him to his Family, obſerve him in his dealings with men, in acts of Juſtice, mind him in his ſobriety, and though hee may bee quick and nimble, yet hee leaves his ſent behind him, and his own Conſcience will one day purſue him by it.</p>
            <p>I Queſtion not, but an ordinary diſſembler knows himſelf to bee ſo, there is one company of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites that are leſſe apt to ſuſpect themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe great zealots for ſome peices of Gods ſervice,
<pb facs="tcp:64705:3"/>
whereby they think they make God amends for the neglect of others: but alas, one ſtring out of tune ſpoils the Muſick: one vain opened, will let out all the bloud in the body, one little hole will let in water enough to drown the Ship: This No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is excellently diſcuſſed in this Sermon: as alſo the abſolute neceſſity of obſerving all the duties, we owe to our Neighbours, if wee will avoid the charge of Hypocriſy, both which with many other things being of excellent uſe for the preſent <hi>canting, talking,</hi> but not <hi>doing</hi> Chriſtians, I thought my friend ſerved the intereſt of piety, by publiſhing this diſcourſe, the judicious reader, I am confident will finde the Author much a Schollar, much a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in it, all that know him have teſtimony of both in his converſe; I am one who have reaſon to bleſſe God for his good example, and for this Sermon which with advantage I heard in the Univerſity, That it may be a bleſſing to thee alſo, ſhall bee the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake, Sam. Jacombe.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lumbardſtreet London.</hi>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64705:3"/>
            <head>TO The Authors beſt Beloved and Honoured Friend, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Hunt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, I hope the Author of this diſcourſe will have no reaſon to bee angry, that I have expoſed his papers to publick view; but if hee ſhould chance to bee arreſted with any ſudden paſsion, I doubt not but hee will bee inſtantly calmed, when hee meets with your name at the entrance, which I know to bee ſo pleaſing unto him, that hee cannot think of it without a ſmile, and a ſmooth forehead. It is a general good that I aim at in ſending them abroad, (many things of great concernment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my poor judgement treated of in
<pb facs="tcp:64705:4"/>
them) but yet I am ſure the Author will bee glad that I have made them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſerve a particular end, and give te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony by this ſhort dedication of the ſingular and dear affection which hee bears to you.</p>
            <p>I will not go about to divine what entertainment they will meet withall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, but I can more than gueſs how you will embrace and kiſs the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of a minde that could not bring forth any thing into the world, without expoſing (as a twin together with it) its great love to you; and how welcome any thing that deſigns to advance pure religion and undefiled, will bee to your ſoul. For I have obſerved ſuch a ſtrange compliance between you and him, that it hath made mee ſometimes think it was great pitty, you did not both ſuck the ſame breaſts, or rather lie together and
<pb facs="tcp:64705:4"/>
embrace in the ſame womb, that there might not have been that little thing wanting, to have made you twin-Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; or I am ready to entertain the Jewiſh fancy (though upon a different ground) that ſouls come into being by pairs, and that you are one of thoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py couples, by whom a more maſculine and generous love, than that which they make to bee the effect of ſuch an union is revived and commended to thoſe who are of your familiarity. And how great an affection I have likewiſe diſcerned in you to the holy truths of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, I will not ſay; knowing that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, humility, and ſelf-denyal are among thoſe that you judge the greateſt devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to bee due unto. I cannot tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any thing in the diſcourſe is through careleſneſs and non-attendancy, ſhort of, or contrary unto the Authors ſenſe,
<pb facs="tcp:64705:5"/>
or whether hee might finde reaſon to correct any thing upon a ſecond review; but I am certain there is nothing here ſaid to you which hee would make any alteration in, or finde any fault with, unleſſe it bee that I have not writ e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of his love, and your merit. As for my ſelf it is no matter who I am. Though I give you but half of my name, yet I am wholly yours, as much as hee can bee, and none knows ſo well as hee how much I honour you,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ric. Patius.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March 25. 1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64705:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Hypocritical Nation deſcribed.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ZACH. 7.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When you faſted and mourned in the fifth and ſeventh month, even thoſe ſeventy years, did you at all faſt unto mee, even to mee?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are part of the anſwer which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet gives to a queſtion, that the people returned out of captivity, had by their meſſengers propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Prieſts, and (as it ſhould ſeem) in caſe they could not reſolve them, to the Prophet, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which wee read in the third verſe of this Chapter. For the better underſtanding both the Queſtion and the Anſwer; wee muſt obſerve, that after the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and their being carried captive by the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed certain faſts to bee kept at ſome ſet times of the year, which were ſad commemorations of that ruine which by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees God had brought upon them. In the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> wee read but of one Faſt (that I remember) commanded by God to this people, which was in the ſame month with one of theſe, <hi>viz. the tenth day of the ſeventh month,</hi> and it is mentioned, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.29.31. <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The neglect, or rather hypocritical obſervance of which <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or day of reſt (for ſo there it is called) is reproved very ſharply in the 58. of <hi>Iſa.</hi> through the whole chapter; where by <hi>Sabbath, verſ.</hi> 13. is to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood this <hi>faſting day on the tenth of the ſeventh month,</hi> and not the ſeventh day of the week. But as there were many occaſional Faſts appointed (as is clear in the hiſtory of the Bible) by the ſupream magiſtrate; ſo upon the carrying of the Nation cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, their Rulers (it is moſt like) did appoint four Faſts to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved every year; which are mentioned altogether, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.19.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64705:6"/>
and were in remembrance (as both ancient and modern, Chriſtian, and Jewiſh Interpreters conjecture) of ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral remarkables in their ruine. <hi>The Faſt of the fourth month</hi> was in memory of the <hi>firſt breach made in the wall of Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem by the Chaldeans,</hi> of which wee read, <hi>Jer.</hi> 52.6, <hi>&amp;c. The Faſt of the fifth,</hi> in memory of the <hi>burning of the Temple,</hi> which in that month happened, (<hi>Jer.</hi> 52.12.) as the burning of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond by <hi>Titus</hi> alſo did. That <hi>of the ſeventh,</hi> was in memory of <hi>the ſlaughter of</hi> Gedaliah, <hi>by</hi> Iſhmael, of which wee read, <hi>Jer.</hi> 41. That of the <hi>tenth month,</hi> in memory of <hi>the beginning of that fiedge which proved ſo fatal to them,</hi> which fell out to bee in that month 2 <hi>King.</hi> 25.1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 52.3.</p>
            <p>But they being now returned to their own Land, and the Temple being begun to bee rebuilt by <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> it comes into their minde to enquire of the Lord, whether they ſhould keep that Faſt any longer, which was in memory of its deſtruction, (for concerning that only their ſcruple is moved, <hi>verſe</hi> 3.) <hi>The Prophet</hi> before hee comes to determine the caſe, and to tell them that the day ſhould ſtill bee obſerved, only with a change of the ſolemnity, that from a <hi>Fast</hi> it ſhould bee turned (together with the reſt) <hi>into a Feaſt,</hi> as it is in the 8 <hi>chap.</hi> 19. I ſay before this hee gives them to underſtand what a true Faſt is (leſt afterward their daies of mirth ſhould bee to no better purpoſe, than their daies of ſorrow) and tells them plainly, that they were much miſtaken, if they thought that they had obſerved a true <hi>Faſt to God</hi> all this while, in the fifth or the ſeventh month either, or had ſerved God better than their Fore-Fathers did, whoſe faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is by God in the forementioned place (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.) undervalued and ſleighted as unworthy of his leaſt reſpect. And this hee doth here in the words of my Text, and thoſe that follow, by way of queſtion. <hi>When you faſted in the fifth, &amp;c. did you at all faſt unto mee, even to mee?</hi> or as it is in the Hebrew, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>did you faſt your faſt to mee, I ſay to mee?</hi> which is a phraſe like that, in <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>is it a time for you, I ſay, for you who are</hi> newly delivered by mee, <hi>to dwell in your ſeiled houſes, &amp;c.</hi> So, did you faſt to mee? I ſay, to mee, who have often declared to you, that I care not for theſe outward performances, but love the hearty forſaking of ſin? or was it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Aben-Ezra</hi> interprets it) <hi>becauſe of mee,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64705:6"/>
for my ſake, for my glory, or to do any thing really pleaſing unto mee? or the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may bee ſuppoſed to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Did I command any ſuch Faſt as this unto you?</hi> who bid you faſt on this faſhion? when you eat and drink, <hi>v.</hi> 6. did not you eat? <hi>i. e.</hi> upon your own pleaſure, or did you any thing but eat and drink? juſt ſuch a thing is your faſting. I am no more pleaſed with it, than with your eating and drinking. It is indifferent unto mee, if barely conſidered, whether you faſt, or not. If you had kept no ſuch daies, you had pleaſed mee as well, unleſſe you had kept them better. This is the ſumme of the words. The Faſt which they obſerved, was but as the exerciſe of any ordinary day; if they had taken their repaſt, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed their calling, anointed their heads, done as they uſed at other times, they had found as much acceptance with God, and equally given him content, who looked for other kinde of faſting, as the Prophet tells us, in the 9, 10.11. <hi>verſes</hi> of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>The words then are a <hi>ſharp expoſtulation</hi> with them about their Hypocritical faſting, or a tart anſwer to their ſcruple or doubt (wherein they was very pious, and of a tender conſcience) whether they ſhould ceaſe to faſt or no. And in them theſe things are obvious to bee noted.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>The parties to whom the Anſwer is directed, to the Prieſts and the people of the Land,</hi> which was either becauſe that both of them were guilty, or that both of them came with this inquiry; the people ſeeking to the Prieſts, and they not being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them, comming with the people to the Prophet, as the manner was in difficult caſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>The matter of the Anſwer,</hi> wherein there is 1 <hi>A Conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that indeed they had faſted many years, and yet, 2 <hi>An Abſolute denial,</hi> that they had obſerved any true Faſt all this time; which being propounded to them by way of queſtion, and appeal to their own conſciences, making them judges in their own caſes, doth put the anſwer out of all doubt, and leaves it as a matter clear, evident, and without any the leaſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, true, that they had not faſted at all. Do you your ſelves now tell mee (ſaith the Prophet) in your ſober thoughts, whether you can think, that not eating, weeping, howling, &amp;c. is Gods faſt? No, you have been told often enough of this; are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64705:7"/>
not theſe the words <hi>which the Lord hath cried by the former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, when Jeruſalem was inhabited, and in proſperity, &amp;c.</hi> (ſo theſe words are beſt rendred in the 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.) have not I told your Fathers by all my ſervants while you was in this land, before your captivity, that this was not the Faſt that I have choſen? And yet you their children are in the ſame miſtake, and come confidently to mee, and tell mee of your performing, that which I alwaies upbraided them withall. Mee thinks your own hearts ſhould reprove you, and ſpare mee a labour of giving you any other anſwer.</p>
            <p>I will ſpeak only to the matter of theſe words, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to aſſert the truth of one or both of theſe obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That there is a ſerious, devout, and laborious humbling of a mans ſelf, which is not the true faſting and humiliation that God will accept of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>That if there bee not that which is the true, there will bee but little difference between the other, and none at all.</hi> The ſecond will bee a conſequent of the firſt, and therefore in the clearing of that, it will ſufficiently bee ſpoken unto.</p>
            <p>The former lies open enough before our eyes in the Text, and hee muſt bee very careleſſe that doth not obſerve this people to have been very contrite in ſome inſtances, and to have expreſſed a great deal of ſorrow, much afflicted themſelves, and that in ſo ſerious a manner, that they thought they had very well pleaſed God, and could not in conſcience leave off theſe exerciſes, till they knew his minde about it, and yet, that they were but idlely imploied all this time, and had as good have been doing the quite contrary thing. They themſelves durſt confidently avouch the truth of the firſt part of what I affirm, and God hee as peremptorily aſſerts the other, and makes their conſciences return as much to themſelves, while hee ſaith, did you faſt unto mee, &amp;c. though this was not the firſt time neither, that hee had told them ſo, and they might have known ſo much before; another as convincing a queſtion following upon this 7. <hi>verſe. Nunquid non ſunt verba quae locutus eſt Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp;c.</hi> (ſo the Vulgar reads them agreeable to the Hebrew) <hi>are not theſe the words which the Lord cryed by the former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, &amp;c.</hi> There is no doubt of it, and I need not go far for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64705:7"/>
proof, for God himſelf directs us to it, if wee will but look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the words of all his Prophets, which are as ſo many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the Text, and as ſo many witneſſes to the truth of what from it I have undertaken to make good; ſome of which I ſhall have occaſion to call in, to atteſt what I affirm, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>That wee may not therefore put a cheat upon our ſelves, and think wee do God good ſervice upon ſuch a day as this, while wee are an abomination to him, and the hated of his ſoul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our Hypocriſie; I ſhall ſhew you</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>What is not Gods Faſt which this people did obſerve.</hi> What this humiliation is that God will not accept?</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>What is Gods Faſt which this people did not, but ſhould have obſerved?</hi> Or what more is required to the pleaſing God, and being accepted of him.</p>
            <p>While I ſpeak of the former of theſe two, I will not quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all notice of the latter, nor keep it altogether from your view, till this be diſpatched, but ſhall reflect ſome light upon it, as I am opening of this, and ſo make fewer words neceſſary for the clearing of it, when my diſcourſe is deſcended to it, and get a liberty thereby, to croud into the narrow compaſſe of this hour, ſome material conſiderations concerning the ſtate of this people, which will conduce very much to the illuſtrating of the whole buſineſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Gods Faſt is not meer abſtinence from food, from either the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacies, or the ordinary refreſhments of nature,</hi> which this people did moſt punctually and nicely obſerve, and alſo tell us that to <hi>the afflicting of the ſoul</hi> of a man (by which phraſe the great Faſt is expreſſed, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.) there are four things required be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide not taſting any food, <hi>viz. abſtaining from,</hi> or laying aſide <hi>their bathes, their ointments, their wives, and their ſhooes,</hi> i. e. every thing that might bee a pleaſure and delight to their bodies. And theſe may ſeem to bee included in that phraſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. of this chapter, <hi>Shall I weep in the fifth month</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>ſeparating my ſelf as I have done theſe many years?</hi> but alas! theſe ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amounted to a labour about nothing, becauſe while they would not for a world touch a bit of bread, they drunk in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity like water, and was filled with it, even to an exceſſe, and it broke out like a ſore diſeaſe; while they pined their body,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64705:8"/>
their luſts, the body of ſin was fat, and well liking; while they took down their fleſh, and made their faces look thin, that which the Scripture calls fleſh, was luſty, ſtrong, pampered, and high fed. Their proud and big thoughts were not taken down, their inordinate covetous deſires were not impaired, their luxurious appetites were not retrenched, nothing that was unreaſonable in them was paired off, moderated, or abated. And ſo their Faſt was to no more purpoſe (not being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned) than if they had been feeding themſelves with more plentiful than ordinary chear. And if wee intend no more to day, than what they performed, wee had as good have gone and made a feaſt, invited our neighbours, and paſſed away that time merrily, which wee are now ſpending only upon a ſad ceremony. If wee conſider the ſimple act, either of the one, or the other of theſe things, neither of them are good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but as they are deſigned by us to certain purpoſes which are good, ſo they come to bee acts of religion. And faſting then from food is good and profitable.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>When in reſpect of the time paſt, it is an act of ſorrow and grief, of anger and diſpleaſure againſt,</hi> and of <hi>revenge upon our ſelves,</hi> for the abuſe of thoſe good things which God hath given us leave to feed upon to our refreſhment, but which wee have fatted our ſelves withall to an exceſſive fulneſſe and wantonneſſe. When it is an expreſſion of our repentance, and diſclaiming of our former courſes, an acknowledgement that wee deſerve nothing at all, but to have our daily food taken away from our tables, and not ſo much as the ſcraps left behinde of that plenteous proviſion which God bleſſes us withall.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>When in reſpect of the time to come, it is an act of mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> deſigned to the ſtarving and pining of our luſts, to the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off their proviſion, and withdrawing of their nouriſhment, to the learning of ſobriety, and temperate living, to the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing denial of our own appetites, and croſſing our own deſires. And ſo it is not a buſineſſe for a day, or whoſe efficacie reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es but till night, but hath a deſign upon the whole life, wherein wee are to abſtain as carefully from all exceſſe, yea, from all ſin, as wee do to day from all our food. To which that of the Fathers doth moſt truly accord, who calls faſting (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) a ſymbole of death, it being that which tends to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64705:8"/>
deſtruction of the body, and the taking away its life. It ſhould not only ſignifie that wee are dying to all earthly things, but ſhould bee an inſtrument of death, to take away the life of our luſts, and when it is ſo uſed, as not to bee a whetſtone, to ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en our ſtomacks againſt the next meal, but to bee a knife, to cut and ſlaſh off all the immoderation of our appetites; and in general, to wound and kill our ſins, it is a thing acceptable to God, and hugely ſerviceable to our ſouls. But let us here note two things. 1 <hi>It is to bee uſed, not only to the mortifying of ſome, but of all our luſts and carnal affections.</hi> Wee muſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the food of our appetites after vain glory, and the praiſe of men, riches and great honours in the world. Wee muſt make it an inſtrument to dull and blunt the edge of all our inordinate longings, and to the fixing ſuch deadning conſiderations in us, as may take us quite off from pleaſing our ſelves. So <hi>Clemens Alex.</hi> obſerves that a Chriſtian knows very well the ſecret meaning and aenigmatical ſenſe of faſting upon the fourth, and ſixth dayes of the week, which are called by the names of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury and Venus, <hi>viz. Wedneſday</hi> and <hi>Friday,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, [<hi>Strom. lib.</hi> 7.] he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon learns to faſt through his whole life, from covetouſneſs and voluptuouſneſs. The choice of thoſe daies was to give him a ſecret document and remembrance that hee ſhould pine, and waſte away his covetous and voluptuous deſires, from whence ſpring all manner of evil. And a Chriſtian, ſaith hee, faſts not only according to the Law, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from all evil actions, but according to the perfection of the Goſpel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from all wicked thoughts and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. Theſe daies give him notice what hee is to do in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day of his life, and the Goſpel Faſt is ſo ſtrict, that it will not let an evil thought or affection have its daily food, though they never grow ſo ſtrong as to beget any evil actions, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts their nouriſhment, and intends their mortification, putting the ſoul upon cutting off all thoſe luxuriances, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adherencies which no body obſerves. 2 <hi>It muſt bee obſerved alſo to the learning our appetites to feed upon spiritual things, upon God, and all his holy truths.</hi> When the ſoul is at liberty from its attendance upon the neceſſities of the body, it ſhould ſtirre up its own hunger, and ſatisfie its ſelf with its proper nutriment,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64705:9"/>
and labour ſo to taſte and relliſh its ſweetneſſe, that ever after it may have a longing for it, and obſerve ſet times for its own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt. And ſo the bodies faſt, ſhould bee the ſouls feſtival, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, it not only relieves and refreſhes it ſelf for that preſent, but affects its palate alſo with ſuch a delicious favour of Gods holy commands, that they ſeem ſweeter than the hony, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-comb, and make the ſoul break for the longing that it hath unto thoſe judgements at all times.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>When in reſpect of the time preſent, it is a help to ſelf-examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, prayer, and holy meditation, by freeing the minde from clouds, and obſcure vapours, and ſetting it at liberty from bodily mixtures, and interpoſals, that it may altogether attend upon its own buſineſſe.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Clemens,</hi> [in <hi>Eclog.</hi>] Faſting voids and diſcharges the ſoul of that matter which clogs its ſpirits, and makes it pure, light, and chearful, together with the body in heavenly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. Wee cannot at the ſame time eat, and drink, and taſte pleaſant things, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and bee conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with things ſeparate from all matter, and that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the knowledge only of the minde, as a Philoſopher could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. [<hi>Porphyr. lib.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] And therefore it may bee to very good purpoſe, to abſtain from our daily food, that thereby our ſouls being lightened and exonerated of that dull heavy matter which oppreſſes them, they may more freely and clearly minde their own proper objects which are perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpiritual. When there is this univerſal intendment in our faſting, it becomes of excellent uſe, and ſingular advantage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; but when wee underſtand no more by it, <hi>than the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees did, who faſted indeed twice every week, but were ſtill full of covetouſneſſe, rapine, and exceſſe;</hi> wee ſhall bee loathſome things with all this religion unto God. <hi>For this is not the Faſt which God hath choſen, to pinch and uſe our bodies unkindly for a day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>It is not weeping, wailing, and making lamentation added to our faſting, though this bee done with a great deal of ſadneſſe, and doleful complaints, as the word</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Text gives us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. Their <hi>Planctus</hi> uſed to bee with howling, beating of their heads, or knocking of their breaſts, and ſometimes tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their hair, with ſuch like expreſſions of inward grief
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64705:9"/>
Now they ask the queſtion, verſ. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Shall I weep:</hi> God anſwers here in the Text, <hi>to what purpoſe in your weeping? yet when you make a pittiful moan, a lamentable deal of do, moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter complaints, beſide your weeping, it was nothing unto mee.</hi> For that word in the third <hi>verſe,</hi> is altered here into: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is changed into mourning; God grants more than they ſpoke of, and ſaith, <hi>when you faſted and wept with wailing and lamentation, &amp;c. you did it not unto mee.</hi> And there was as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in all the appendices of this weeping which here wee may conceive not to have been excluded, <hi>viz. rending of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, putting on of ſackcloth, ſtrowing aſhes on their heads, lying upon the ground</hi> (a thing in faſhion among Heathens themſelves, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us of the Athenian women, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>ſitting in ſilence, and hanging down their heads, &amp;c.</hi> [L <hi>de Iſid. &amp; Oſir.</hi>] For alas the deep and hearty ſorrow for ſin, the mourning of their ſouls after God, the rending and tearing of their hearts, the doffing off all the fine gay clothing, wherein their ſouls ſecretly prided themſelves, the uncaſeing and ſtripping of their ſouls of all their coverings, wherein they hid and kept warm many beloved ſins, the laying cloſe ſome grating conſiderations to their hearts, the powring ſuch ſhame and reproach upon themſelves, that they ſhould never look God in the face with any confidence, till they were peremptorily reſolved (againſt all impediments) to bee better; theſe things I ſay, they were meer ſtrangers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>And therefore the Prophet cries out,</hi> Iſa. 58.4, 5. <hi>Is this the Faſt that I have choſen, to bow down his heard as a Bulruſh, &amp;c? Wilt thou call this a Faſt, and an acceptable day to the Lord? &amp;c. No, rend your hearts, and not your garments, ſaith the Prophet</hi> Joel, <hi>turn unto the Lord with faſting, weeping, and mourning.</hi> Then tears are good, when they are the companions of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting and a returning heart, when they run out of a ſoul that is running towards God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2, 3. <hi>All the houſe of Iſrael la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented after the Lord, and Samuel ſpake unto them, ſaying, if you return unto the Lord with all your heart, then put away the ſtrange Gods, and prepare your heart to the Lord, and ſerve him only, and hee will deliver you,</hi> i. e. If you bee in good earneſt, let us ſee ſomething beſide your weeping and lamentation, and if theſe bee the outward expreſſions of the inward relenting of your,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64705:10"/>
hearts, then put away all thoſe diſpleaſing things that have created you ſo much miſchief, and coſt you now ſo many tears, &amp;c. This people here in the Text might mourn and weep, if it had but been to think of the great calamities that had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faln them, the ruine of their City, the burning of their Temple, the captivity of their Nation, the pouring out their blood like water, and ſundry doleful circumſtances in all theſe, which might make them wiſh <hi>with Jeremiah, that their head was waters, and their eyes fountains of tears, that they might weep day and night for the ſlain, of the daughter of their people,</hi> Jer. 9.1. But what is all this to a ſenſe of ſin and a groaning under the intollerable burden of their iniquity! to what purpoſe are all theſe tears, if inward anguiſh and grief for ſin, do not give them all their acrimony and ſmartneſſe, if they waſh and cleanſe not the ſoul from its filth and naſtineſs? Or ſuppoſe there was ſome preſent ſenſe of ſin, which expreſſed theſe briny tears; alas! they were but like a ſudden daſh of rain, which is ſoon paſſed over, and then all is clear again. At the next meeting they entertained their ſins with as great a friendſhip and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity, as if there had been never any falling out, nor any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſes paſt between them. Such are the tears of many a one, that cozens himſelf into a conceit that hee is a penitent; they are the iſſue of a natural tenderneſſe, or the product of ſome ſharp affliction, or the overflow of ſome ſudden paſſion, which are but like to thoſe which flow from the eyes of a young man, who being in love with one hugely below him, and therefore chidden by his Father, weeps like a little childe, and ſeems as though hee would drown himſelf in the flood of his tears, but upon the very next ſight is as hot in his love, and as eager in his purſuit, as though there had been no ſuch cooler. Tears are no further liked of God, than as they are expreſſions of a ſerious inward grief and ſorrow, and then only are they expected from us, when wee uſe to weep in other caſes of ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and upon doleful accidents. If that bee our temper to weep bitterly, when ſome mournful object preſents it ſelf to us, wherein wee are concerned; it is a ſad ſign to ſee our eyes drye, when the deplorable condition of our ſouls do lye before us; but if our ſorrow uſe to expreſſe it ſelf ſome other way in ſuch caſes, then that is all the outward token that God requires
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64705:10"/>
in this. Yet let it bee what it will, God will not accept of it unleſſe it amount to a great diſpleaſure againſt our ſelves, baſe thoughts of our ſelves, that have committed ſuch acts, a huge trouble in our mind for what is paſt, hearty wiſhes all were undone, ſenſe of our obnoxiouſneſſe to Gods judgements, fear of his diſpleaſure, humble and earneſt requeſts to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into his favour, which laſt thing if it bee true, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with our remaining in a ſtate of ſin; and therefore this ſorrow goes a great deal further, and includes in it, a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſin, a reſolution never more to have to do with it, a chuſing rather to dye, than willingly attempt ſuch another act; an actual declining of it, a ſetting our ſelves to reſiſt the next temptation, a placing of a watch over our ſelves, and in every thing ſuch a temper as cannot bee quiet in the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is, but muſt bee better. If wee finde not our ſelves in this poſture, there is not ſo much as the beginning of that work in us, which God looks for, when <hi>wee faſt, and mourn, and ſeek unto him, viz.</hi> of that through reformation without which wee do not faſt unto him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Large confeſſions of our ſins and prayers to God for the pardon of them, and turning away of his wrath, will not make the Faſt of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Not large confeſſions of ſin, which were uſual upon daies of faſting, as appears from <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. and ſundry other places; and perhaps were not wanting in thoſe Faſts which my Text ſpeaks of. They brought, its moſt likely, before God long ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogues of their own ſins, and of the provocations of their Fore-Fathers, of their Kings, Princes, Prophets, and Prieſts, and they might condemn themſelves, and acknowledge the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgements of God; and yet all this was nothing but their hypocritical dealing with God, while they were in love with thoſe ſins which they did ſo earneſtly confeſſe, and was not in a ſtate of irreconciliation to thoſe iniquities which they cryed out ſo vehemently againſt. This kinde of devotion was far from finding any kinde entertainment with God, and was rather like to meet with a frown and this angry ſentence; <hi>out of your own mouthes ſhall you bee condemned, and periſh, you your ſelves being judges.</hi> This confeſſion ſignifies nothing more (if any thing at all) but that men deſire that they may do ſtill as they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64705:11"/>
were wont to do, and that the acknowledgements of their faults may procure leave to practice the ſame again with no greater trouble, but only to make a new acknowledgement; it ſpeaks only that they are Sinners, and that they deſire they may ſo ſtill bee, and they will not ſtick to make an open confeſſion of it. Yea, whatſoever men may mean by it, this confeſſion ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies nothing at all unto God; for the ſins that men reherſe are known unto God before, and are all preſent before him; if that bee all they have to ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> that they are Sinners, and have committed ſuch and ſuch acts againſt God, they may as well let their tongues bee quiet, there is nothing new in all this. Then confeſſion is ſignificant, when it is an act of ſhame and reproach to our ſelves, an act of grief and hatred, a diſavow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſclaiming ſuch practiſes. Now wee ſay ſomething unto God; this is a new buſineſs, and the caſe is quite altered; there is forgiveneſſe with God for ſuch perſons, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. and what <hi>Solomon</hi> prayes for in the behalf of ſuch Supplicants, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.47, 48. God himſelf promiſeth unto them, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14. True confeſſion ſignifies that wee are aſhamed, that wee have nothing to ſay for our ſelves, that we cannot but cry out againſt our own baſeneſs and falſeneſs to God; that wee would rather not bee, than do one ſuch vile act again; that wee are grieved and pained at the very heart, and cannot but vent our ſelves in ſighs and groans, that wee cannot with patience think upon our ſelves, and cannot hold from proclaiming our own guiltineſſe, that wee remember nothing with ſo much ſadneſſe, as that wee have been ſinners, and that wee reſolve by Gods aſſiſtance and our utmoſt indeavours, to bee better, may wee but bee pardoned ſuch offences. God loves ſuch a pungent ſorrow as pricks to the very heart, and gives a deadly wound to our ſins, ſuch a grief as ſtrikes through the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life of our luſts, and nails them to the croſs. Hee loves, when wee look upon him whom wee have peirced, and mourn bitterly; ſo that our hearts are ſtruck through with an incure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wound to the fleſh, and all the affections and deſires there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and hee loves ſuch a confeſſion as expreſſes this ſorrow, this pain, and this torment of our hearts, which will bee mixed with a vehement diſpleaſure and hatred, both againſt our ſelves, and our ſins, and then hee willingly imbraces us; this is part of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64705:11"/>
the <hi>Faſt which hee hath choſen;</hi> but whatſoever volumes wee bring in againſt our ſelves without this, they are but hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal talk before God, and will not avail us, yea will harm us, becauſe wee lye under this dangerous deceit, that ſome one good action will commend us to God, without all the reſt, and ſo even our ſeriouſneſſe in ſome one thing, will bee our undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and keep us from the practiſe of all other neceſſary duties.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>As for Prayer, it is plain, the Jews neglected not that in their Faſts,</hi> but it was commonly to no other purpoſe, but that <hi>God would pardon them, turn again unto them, and ſave them from the hands of their enemies,</hi> while they thought not of turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto him, and putting all his enemies out of their ſouls; and therefore hee tells them that which I aſſert as the ſecond branch of this particular, <hi>that this is not the Faſt which hee hath choſen, to cauſe their voice to bee heard on high, viz.</hi> either in mournful howlings, or in clamorous petitions, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.4. <hi>and that when they faſt, hee will not hear their cry, &amp;c.</hi> Jer. 14.12. <hi>For hee that turns away his ear from hearing of the Law, even his prayer ſhall bee an abomination,</hi> Prov. 28.9. <hi>If men will not hear God, hee will not hear them:</hi> I had almoſt ſaid hee cannot give ear to them, there being ſome things, that either in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or in the method of Gods proceedings in the government of the world, are altogether inconſiſtent with the bleſſings which wee deſire, or are the cauſes of thoſe evils which wee groan under; and therefore unleſſe wee heartily renounce to all thoſe things, and throughly diſcharge them, our prayers for mercies, and for removal of miſeries, are a peece of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, incoherent, ignorant ſtuffe, which will bee thrown as dung in our faces.</p>
            <p>When men bear a love to thoſe ſins which they pray may not ruine them, and the evil conſequents of which they deſire may bee prevented or remedied, they are as ridiculous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſſeful, as if a man ſhould begge health, while hee continues in his riotous, and intemperate courſe of living. Let a man raiſe his confidence by what arts hee pleaſe, and ſpeak with a boldneſſe in his prayers, as though hee could command hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and have what hee would of God, yet hee cannot have any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64705:12"/>
true faith that hee ſhall bee heard, unleſſe hee utterly abandon in heart and reſolution, whatſoever is incompatible, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with the things that hee deſires. Wee may call our Faſts by the name of daies of prayer (as wee commonly do) but though wee ſhould pray from morning until night, though the whole Nation ſhould cry to God, that hee would bow the heavens, and come to ſave us, and that with a voice that would rend the clouds, and ſeem to make way for him, to come down to us; yet if wee bee in love with the cauſes of our trouble, wee have put in ſuch a ſtrong caveat, ſuch a barre to our ſuits and petitions in the Court of Heaven, that wee can have no audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Yea further, though wee ſhould bee distaſted againſt our ſins, though wee ſhould reſolve amendment, and therefore begge divine grace to deſtroy our iniquities;</hi> yet this will not compleat Gods Faſt, neither if wee reſolve to bee at no trouble, nor pains about this buſineſſe, but leave all to the care of God, whom wee would have ſo farre to concern himſelf in our buſineſſe, as not to expect that wee ſhould bee ſuch creatures as hee made us. Such prayers will have a perfect likeneſſe to the requeſts of the man in the fable, to <hi>Hercules,</hi> when his Cart ſtuck in the mire, who would neither prick forward the Oxen, nor lay his own ſhoulders to the wheels, but caſt all upon the ſtrength of his God, expecting that hee ſhould come and draw them out; and ſuch an anſwer will bee moſt fitly returned to ſuch petitions as was to him,
<q>
                  <l>O bone, diſce pigris non flecti numina votis</l>
                  <l>Praſenteſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> adhibi, quam facis ipſe, Deos.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Learn good Sir, that God is not moved by lazy deſires, and ſluggiſh wiſhes, and that thou ſhalt then finde God preſent when thou thy ſelf art buſy about thy work.</p>
            <p>I may adde further, that the caſe may ſo bee, that though there bee ſome good men in a Nation, that do moſt ſeriouſly and heartily pray for it, they may not bee able to help them, and that not bee the Faſt of God, unto which truth I might call in the Teſtimony of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> in <hi>cap.</hi> 11.14. and 14.11. <hi>where God bids him not pray for that people, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64705:12"/>
               <hi>v.</hi> 8.44. where hee ſaith, <hi>that when hee did cry and ſhout, God ſhut out his prayers, and covered himſelf with a cloud, that their prayer could not paſſe through.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like teſtimony <hi>Ezekiel</hi> would afford us, who tells us more than once, Chap. 14. that in ſome caſes three ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent perſons as <hi>Noah, Job, and Daniel, ſhall obtain no more than their own ſecurity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I might have all their ſuffrages to this, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times nothing leſſe than an univerſal reformation (in the great Officers, Magiſtrates, and Governours eſpecially) will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Gods favour, but I have already ſtaid ſo long upon this head, that the time calls mee to haſten to a concluſion of it. <hi>Then therefore Prayers are to good purpoſe for our ſelves, or the Nation, when wee or the Nation come to God with a holy diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of heart to forſake our ſins, and with a readineſſe of heart to make uſe of that divine grace which wee beg at his hands, with a reſolution to do that our ſelves which wee deſire God ſhould do for us;</hi> When they are inſtruments to Piety and Godlineſſe, and put our hearts into ſuch a holy frame, that even by our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wee may pray and pull down the bleſſings of heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us.</p>
            <p>For as <hi>Clemens Alex.</hi> ſpeaks of a ſpiritual heavenly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his whole life is a Prayer to God, and a familiar converſe with him. Hee prays all day long in ſome ſort, <hi>viz.</hi> as to the effect and iſſue of Prayer, the holyneſſe of his life, ſpeaking power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and effectually in his behalf to God, if not more preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, becauſe it is the uſe and the improvement of that grace, which we have received, and ſo directly intitles us to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings that are in that promiſe, <hi>To him that hath ſhall be giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet wee muſt take notice of this, that when wee pray thus to the reforming and amending of our hearts and lives, the bleſſings wee are moſt confidently to expect, are thoſe of a ſpiritual and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal nature;</hi> ſuch as are forgiveneſs of ſin, acceptance with God to life, and that we cannot bee certain ſometimes, that by all our Reformation wee ſhall avert temporal judgements, upon our own perſons, or our Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64705:13"/>And ſo I am aſcended one ſtep higher than I was before. Perhaps the Decree may bee irrevocably gone forth, the ruine of a people, or perſon may bee abſolutely determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or at leaſt ſome very ſharp puniſhment, without any poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of reverſing the ſentence, may bee reſolved upon, and though the ſin may bee forgiven to ſome (and thoſe the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) purpoſes, yet not unto all. Who can tell whether God will return and repent, was all that could bee ſaid in the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivites</hi> caſe; and in the caſe of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> it was at laſt decree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that their City and Temple ſhould bee deſtroyed, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hopes of prevention of ſuch a calamity, though they had ſpace given them to repent in, that their ſouls might find mercy with God. And this is our ſatisfaction that when wee faſt and pray aright, wee ſhall partake of the principal benefits that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon them, though not alwaies of all the fruits and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which have thereby been procured.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>I might adde, that to bee good a while after wee have faſted, confeſſed our ſins, and prayed, is not the faſt of God, which will quite turn away his wrath from us.</hi> That which God expects is an eternal divorce between us and our ſins, and that wee ſeek him with our whole heart, ſo as to continue in well doing; elſe with our return again to folly; the ſtripes which are for the back of fools, will return alſo. And commonly the caſe is more dangerous, and the diſeaſe harder to cure, when wee do relapſe after wee were well recovered. The holy ſtory is ſo clear in this, that hee muſt bee much unacquainted with the condition of theſe people in all thoſe times, that doth not ſee it, and therefore knowing every one can furniſh himſelf with proofs enough if hee do but read any one book of their Hiſtory, I ſhall herein ſpare my further labor.</p>
            <p n="5">5 And laſtly, <hi>Though all this bee done out of conſcience, and wee would not for any good omit theſe performances, but in the honeſty of our heart obſerve daies of faſting, times of confeſſion, and conſtant prayer, and have very pious intentions in the buſineſſe,</hi> yet it will not make up <hi>the fast which God require;</hi> Such was the Temper of this people, as I noted in the beginning of this diſcourſe. They was ſcrupulous in their conſciences, very loath to diſpleaſe God by neglecting good duties; but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64705:13"/>
alas! poor ſouls, this was the Hypocryſy which the Scripture ſo much ſpeaks of, the finer ſort of Hypocriſy, I ſay, that carries ſo many to Hel, in a pleaſing beleef that they are going to heaven, while they are ſerious and zealous in ſome things, but not in all. They faſted ſeverely, they mourned very bitterly, knocked their breaſts very heartily, confeſſed very devoutly, and prayed very earneſtly, but yet they did not <hi>ſearch and try their ways, to turn again unto the Lord,</hi> they did not every one <hi>put away the evil of their doings,</hi> and ſo all their zeal in the former things, inſtead of doing them good, wrought their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er miſchief, by making them confidently to account them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves religious perſons, and to bee angry with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who would perſwade them to the contrary.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> will fully inform us how God valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their diligence and forwardneſs in ſuch ſervices. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your ſacrifices? I am full of burnt offerings &amp;c. (I even nauſeat the plenty of theſe devotions) when you come to appear before mee, who hath required this at your hands? &amp;c. The Sabbaths, The calling of Aſſemblies, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not away with, it is iniquity, even the ſolemn meeting, your new Moons, &amp;c. are a trouble to me, I am weary to bear them, &amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 1.11, 12, 13. &amp;c. This is worſe than all the reſt, that men can ſee ſo much reaſon to do all theſe things, and yet will ſee no reaſon to be good; that they will have God to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with what pleaſes them, and gives no great diſtaſte to their natures, but will not part with any thing that they dearly love, though it be the greateſt offence to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It were well now if every one would examine his own heart, and give himſelf an account, whether hee have done thus much as the people of the Jews here mentioned did, and then whether hee have done any more.</hi> There are not many it is like that have thus faſted, and wept, and prayed, but I doubt they are rarely to bee found (one perhaps of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand) that make a conſcience not to ſin, and to keep a faſt every day to God, by the conſtant practice of mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and holy living.</p>
            <p>I leave it to the private ſcrutiny of every mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64705:14"/>
to finde whether or no hee bee in the number of thoſe that obſerve the faſt of God, and I think I have ſaid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to let him know the ſtate of his ſoul, if hee will impartially ranſack his heart, and have no minde to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen himſelf. If it bee neceſſary further to aſſiſt him, the explication of the ſecond truth which I propoſed to bee conſidered, will I hope, contribute ſome further help to his ſincere ſearch, both into his own condition, and of the whole Nation, unto which I ſhall now betake my ſelf, and ſhow</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>What the true faſt of God is which this people did not, but ſhould have obſerved, and ſo what is further required to the rendring us acceptable to God.</hi> This hath been ſo much touched upon in the former argument, that leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains now due to the unfolding of it, except it bee what moſt particularly belongs to the opening of this portion of Scripture, and the laying before us the condition of this people, which may bee applicable unto us, as farre as wee are parallel unto them, in which our own obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation will beſt inform us.</p>
            <p>Gods Faſt then is, as you cannot but already acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>a thorow amending of our ways and doings,</hi> and commonly it is <hi>a general, univerſal reformation,</hi> if it bee a general good for which God is ſolicited by us, to which I may adde, eſpecially in the Rulers, Governours, and Leaders of the People, who have a manifeſt influence upon all the reſt, whoſe faſhion ordinarily they will be in, and whoſe ſins therefore are ſometimes alone name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in holy writ, as procuring Gods judgements, becauſe by their neglect, and ill example, the reſt run more pronely into all wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe there is but a little time more remaining which I can hope your patience will allow mee; I ſhall addreſſe my ſelf to treat particularly of that which God required of this People, who came to bee enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by him in relation to their faſting, and wee may bring it home to our own condition, according as we ſhall find juſt cauſe and reaſon ſo to do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64705:14"/>
               <hi>God you have heard upbraides them here in the Text with their hypocritical, partial faſting,</hi> and therefore proceeds in the 9. and 10. verſes, to acquaint them what faſt it was that hee alwayes called for, and expected, which he doth again in the 8. Chap. 16, 17. which places I deſire you will take the pains to conſult.</p>
            <p>And then I doubt not but you will ſee reaſon for this obſervation, that the ſins they were chiefly guilty of more than others, <hi>were neglects of the duties of the ſecond Table,</hi> (as wee ſpeak) <hi>not performing of thoſe offices which one man owes unto another; but violent breaking all thoſe bonds whereby men are tyed by God together,</hi> and therefore that theſe things were carefully to bee reformed by their faſting and prayer. They may be reduced to theſe three heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt dealing and defrauding one another, by lying, falſe ſwearing, deviſing to over-reach and ruite their brethren. Speak every man the truth to his Neighbour, execute the judgement of truth, imagine not evil, love not a falſe oath,</hi> ch. 7.9, 10. cap. 8 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Want of mercy and compaſſion, cruelty, hard, and rigid dealing with their neighbours, and this is as bad as down-right unjuſtice,</hi> chap. 7.9. <hi>ſhew mercy, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Oppreſſion of the poor, and thoſe that could not right them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the mighty,</hi> ch. 7.10. <hi>oppreſs not the widdow, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this was chiefly the fault of the great ones, of the rich, the rulers and governours.</p>
            <p>Concerning all theſe and ſuch like ſins, wee muſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſerve that they were the iniquities of their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, and ſo hard it ſeems it was to cure theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers (either becauſe they are ſo dearly beloved, or elſe ſo little regarded, while men have a conceit of their purity in religion) that theſe perſons, their Children, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main guilty of the very ſame faults.</p>
            <p>God here tells them, <hi>what words hee had ſpoken to their Fathers by the Prophets of old</hi> (as I have noted before) verſ. 7. who for theſe, together with two other ſins; <hi>viz. Sabbath breaking and idolatry,</hi> were turned out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64705:15"/>
land; there are indeed other ſins mentioned by the Prophets, but none ſo much inſiſted upon as theſe, to bee the cauſe of their <hi>expulſion out of the good land, and baniſhment into a ſtrange Country,</hi> as you ſhall diſcern before I have gone much further.</p>
            <p>Now it ſeems that their poſterity (theſe men in the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity) was grown more obſervant of the Sabbath, and greater haters of Idolatry, and becauſe of their religious ſervices which were more pure, took themſelves for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good men, though they retained <hi>their Fathers injuſtice and fraud, cruelty, and numercifulneſſe, oppreſſion and violent dealing.</hi> Which was plainly the caſe of the Phariſees (the poſterity of theſe perſons) in our Saviours time, before this their laſt and long captivity; they were notoriouſly guilty of theſe ſins, more than of any other, while they could not bee challenged with any idolatrous practiſes, or with neglect of the Sabbath day, no nor with leſſe ſtrictneſſe in any other religious performances. Under their Religion they cloaked their unrighteouſneſſe, and made all their piety good for nothing, being ſtained with covetouſneſſe, oppreſſion of the widdows, and thoſe that had no helpers, with ſuch like wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>From all which, wee may bee bold to affirm ſtill, that God proceeds in ſuch a manner with Nations, that where theſe ſins do remain; it is in vain to faſt, and pray, and cry to God for mercy, yea to reform in other matters which concern Gods worſhip and ſervice; about which commonly moſt of the noiſe is made, out of hopes that their prayers, and their preaching, and other religious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, together with the aſſerting of theſe from ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and impurities, will drown the cry of injuſtice, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, blood, oppreſſion, and ſuch like ſins, of the which, that wee may bee the more ſenſible; I ſhall digeſt what remains into theſe particular conſiderations; and make appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That this of old, was the Faſt which God required of their Fathers by the Prophets, viz. that they ſhould forſake theſe ſins which I have mentioned.</hi> And that hee every
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64705:15"/>
where urges, even in the moſt reforming times, their growing more juſt, merciful, &amp;c. in their dealings, and their practiſing thoſe duties which ariſe from the reſpect that one man hath to another.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>That after their return from the captivity of</hi> Babylon, <hi>ſtill theſe things, more than any elſe are inſiſted upon, as thoſe they were deficient in, and ſhould amend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>That theſe are noted as the waſting and deſtroying ſins, though there ſhould bee no other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>That where men expect peace, ſettlement, quiet, and removeal of judgements in a Nation, they muſt have an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial care to reform in theſe particulars.</hi> And above other things theſe are to be minded in our humiliation, becauſe commonly in theſe, Nations are moſt guilty, and men are apt to imagine, that ſome religious duties are the great matters that God expects.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That theſe, of old, were the things the Prophets inſiſted upon, is the firſt thing to bee cleared.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> offers himſelf a witneſſe in the very firſt chapter of his viſion, where hee findes no fault for their Idolatry, nor queſtions the legality of their ſacrifices, nor charges them with praying to ſtrange Gods, nor blames for with-holding his due oblations from him; no, on the contrary, hee acknowledges <hi>a multitude of ſacrifices, that hee was full of burnt offerings, that they obſerved their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Feaſts, and ſolemn meetings, and made many prayers,</hi> but hee tells them, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>that hee could not indure to look upon them, when they ſpread their hands towards heaven, becauſe thoſe hands were full of blood,</hi> and therefore the thing hee calls for, is, <hi>that they would waſh and cleanſe their hands of that blood which had be ſmeared them, that they would put away their injuſtice, oppreſſion, unmercifulneſs, &amp;c.</hi> and then <hi>if they came and prayed, hee would ſpeak friendly to them, and have a parly with them, and do away thoſe bloody crimſon ſins, and reſtore them by their repentance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment to a Snow-like whiteneſſe, as if they had been as innocent as Lambs, and not ſo ravenous as Lions,</hi> read <hi>verſ.</hi> 16, 17, 18. and obſerve to whom it is that hee ſpeaks, <hi>viz.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64705:16"/>
to the rulers firſt</hi> (who were like <hi>Sodom) and then to the people (who were not far diſtant from them in this wickedneſſe, being like to Gomorrah) ver.</hi> 9. <hi>I ſay of the Rulers firſt, who had</hi> the deepeſt ſhare in this guilt, and were the ring-leaders in theſe ſins, as will appear to him that ſhall but caſt his eye upon the 21, 22, 23, 26. <hi>verſes.</hi> I will not yet diſmiſſe this witneſſe, who ſpeaks ſo fully and cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the buſineſſe. Bee pleaſed ſeriouſly to read the 58. <hi>chap. ver.</hi> 4, 6, 7. and then tell mee <hi>what Faſt it was that God called for in thoſe times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And likewiſe thoſe woes againſt them that decree un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous decrees, and that write grievouſneſſe which they have preſcribed <hi>to turn aſide the needy from judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to take away the right from the poor, &amp;c. cap.</hi> 10. 1, 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 30. 12, 13. and then tell mee what ſins they were much guilty of.</p>
            <p>Hee that will take the pains duly to conſider theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, will finde ſo many other bordering upon them, to the ſame purpoſe, that hee will bee more ſenſible of the truth of that which I affirm, and I ſhall have occaſion to call in the aſſiſtance of many of them before I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p>I ſhall next deſire you to hear what the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> informs us concerning this matter, who lived in the ſame time with <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> And mee thinks hee ſpeaks ſtill more plainly (if it bee poſſible ſo to do) crying out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe ſins more than againſt others, eſpecially in their rulers. The woes in the 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 1, 2. (which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you read) <hi>are againſt thoſe, who becauſe they had power in their hands, contrived how to greaten themſelves, though with the ruine of others;</hi> and if they ſaw but a fair field, or a houſe which they had a minde unto, <hi>would by violence take it away, though it was the mans inheritance, and tended to his undoing.</hi> And in the 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 1, 2, 3. hee ſpeaks of moſt cruel and butcherly actions; <hi>the flaying and peiling of the people to the very bones;</hi> yea, and after one would think that they had brought them low enough, yet they would <hi>have no pitty upon theſe poor Skeleton's, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64705:16"/>
broke their very bones, and chopt them in peeces, as one doth when hee puts fleſh in the pot;</hi> i. e. <hi>they utterly devoured them, and eat them up;</hi> and it is obſerveable, that at the very ſame time <hi>they built up Zion and Jeruſalem with this blood, ver.</hi> 9, 10, 11. i. e. <hi>they beautified the Temple,</hi> and repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or enlarged the City, and was reformers of things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe or decayed in Gods worſhip at the coſt and charges of many a poor innocent, that they had rent in peeces, and ſhared amongſt them. What is all this but that which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> told us, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.10, 21, 23. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>chap.</hi> 3, 13, 14.15. where hee reproves the Elders and great ones for their <hi>beating his people to peeces, and grinding the faces of the poor,</hi> for which hee was come to call them to a reckoning, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. The Rulers then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo bad, there is little reaſon to expect much juſtice or mercy among the people, who alſo <hi>oppreſſed and offered violence one to another,</hi> as far as their power would reach, for proof of which ſpare not to read, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.10, 11, 12. and likewiſe the ſix firſt verſes of the ſeventh chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which tells us largely of the <hi>general cruelty, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, treachery, &amp;c. both of the Princes and all the people, though never ſo nearly related one to another;</hi> ſo that it was as hard to finde a merciful and a juſt man, as to finde a bunch of Grapes after the Vintage. And therefore in the ſixth chapter, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. &amp;c. God by the ſame Prophet calls not <hi>for their ſacrifices and religious ſervices</hi> (which it ſeems they were frank enough in, and could have been content to have been at any expence about, ſo they might but quietly keep their covetous, griping, and devouring luſts and deſires) <hi>but to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If wee draw nearer to the time of the firſt captivity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Babylon,</hi> wee ſhall hear no new Sermons, but the very ſame ſins ſtill reproved, and laid before them to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of. <hi>Zephaniah</hi> will bee our informer in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who lived in the daies of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> who was a reformer, and with whom it is plain, the Princes joyned (though wee may gueſſe from <hi>chap.</hi> 1, 4, 5. that many of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64705:17"/>
people did not affect their proceedings) to purge the land from Idolatry, and yet read but the five firſt verſes of the third chapter, and you will eaſily diſcern what ſtill was lacking, and how eaſily they would part with any thing (even their Idols) rather than theſe ſins of which I am ſpeaking. And therefore the Prophet exhorts thoſe that had any of theſe rare vertues in them, <hi>any merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and righteouſneſſe,</hi> that they would <hi>go on to practiſe them, and in theſe waies to ſeek the Lord,</hi> and ſaith, it is probable (but not certain) they may bee ſecured in that deluge of miſery, that was like to overflow the whole land, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>And afterward hee propheſies that they ſhould bee the poor, and the afflicted (thoſe that had been oppreſſed, and ſtript naked by the great, and the rich)</hi> who ſhould eſcape, and bee left in the land, when all thoſe mens poſſeſſions were taken from them, and that they ſhould bee ſuch a remnant, <hi>as ſhould not do iniquity, nor ſpeak lies, nor have a deceitful tongue in their mouth,</hi> but ſhall truſt in God, and not in theſe evill arts, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> alſo who propheſied in the daies of the ſame <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and alſo of <hi>Jehoiakim,</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> in the time of both the firſt and ſecond captivity into <hi>Babylon,</hi> and alſo after, hee I ſay, ſpeaks the very ſame words, as will bee very plain to thoſe who will do themſelves ſo much right for the underſtanding of this truth, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.4, 5, 6, 7. where though, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. hee ſpeak <hi>of their offering incenſe to Baal;</hi> yet I ſuppoſe it was the ſin only of ſome of them, who alſo came into the houſe of God in this time of reformation by <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and worſhipped him, though privately it ſhould ſeem they had an Altar for <hi>Baal;</hi> and hee ſpeaks not half ſo much of this Idolatry, as of theſe other ſins; complaining again, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>that his houſe was a denne of Robbers, a meer neſt of Theeves, where a crew of oppreſſors met together, thinking to expiate all by their devotions,</hi> and <hi>chap.</hi> 9. from the ſecond <hi>verſe,</hi> to the ninth, hee bewails theſe ſins, and theſe alone with a ſad and compaſſionate heart, they being the very ſins that undid them, as hee notes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>(through deceit
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64705:17"/>
they refuſe to know mee, ſaith the Lord;)</hi> and as I ſhall ere long come to demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezekiel</hi> likewiſe will witneſſe largely to this truth, who tells us how little they were amended after the firſt captivity in the daies of <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> (when hee prophecied, as appears from <hi>chap.</hi> 1.1.2.) while hee lets us know who the perſons were that God would account righteous, and that ſhould live, and who the wicked perſons were that ſhould bee deſtroyed, <hi>chap.</hi> 18. from the 3. <hi>verſe</hi> to the 19th. and <hi>chap.</hi> 33.14, 15, 25, 26. where though hee mention their Idolatry, yet hee enlarges far more upon theſe other ſins, and the contrary vertues, and notes it as remarkable in them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. of 33. <hi>chap. that they ſtood upon their ſword,</hi> i. e. <hi>did commit violence and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of which the ſword was the inſtrument, and by which they thought to defend and protect themſelves in ſuch practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and this they did, even after they ſaw Gods Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon part of their Nation, not above twelve years before, and the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> were juſt now ready to take their City again, and deſtroy them utterly, as wee may note from <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. <hi>Theſe things they were ſo ſetled in, that it ſeems they made but a mock of thoſe that came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, and to threaten Gods Judgements,</hi> and did but laugh when the Prophets ſaid, that for <hi>theſe ſins they ſhould bee deſtroyed,</hi> and ſodden in their City like fleſh in a pot, (as they themſelves phraſed it in a jeering way, againſt them that would talk of ſuch an unlikely thing) <hi>chap.</hi> 11.3. And therefore the Prophet applies it to another pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and then gives them leave what to think of his threatning, telling them that they had multiplied their ſlain in that City, and filled the ſtreets with them, and hee was ſure that thoſe ſlain might well bee compared to fleſh, and their City to the cauldron, where it had ſoaked, and been ſodden in its own blood, and that their ſaying did better ſet forth their own wickedneſſe, than their puniſhment which they would not beleeve ſhould come, for becauſe of their bloodineſſe they ſhould be ſlain not in the City (where then they hoped for ſecurity) but in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64705:18"/>
border of the Land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whether they fled, hoping that way to ſave themſelves when the City was taken, ve. 6, 7, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>I ſhould bee too tedious ſhould I let you hear all that may bee ſaid in this Argument, and lead you alſo to the ten Tribes, and ſhow you how guilty they were in theſe Matters, and how the Prophets threaten them as well as <hi>Judah</hi> (for which I refer you to the Prophet <hi>Micah,</hi> whoſe Viſion was concerning <hi>Samaria</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> chap. 1.1. and the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> whoſe viſion was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſaw what was comming upon the Kine of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> who did oppreſſe the poor, and cruſh the needy, chap 4.1.) and therefore I will onely obſerve 3 things, which it will bee uſeful to take into our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and will more illuſtrate all this diſcourſe, &amp; ſo paſs to the ſecond thing which I propounded to be ſpoken unto.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Wee cannot but take notice from what hath been ſaid, that even when they were reformed in their divine worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when idolatry and ſuperſtition were caſt out of the Church, yet theſe great abuſes, theſe crying ſins remained among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Temple was purged, the Levites were ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſacrifices according to the Law offered, the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver celebrated in ſuch a manner, that ſcarce ever was the like ſeen, from its firſt inſtitution, the brazen Serpent was broken; and all this, by the conſent of the Princes &amp; Rulers who yet continued <hi>thus unjuſt, cruel, and devouring,</hi> as both <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and <hi>Micah</hi> (who lived in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> time) and <hi>Zephaniah</hi> (who lived in <hi>Joſiahs</hi>) have infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med us very largely; do but conſult the 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.30. and you will finde that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> the King, and the Princes, ordered the worſhip of God, and chap. 35. where you will behold the Princes in <hi>Joſiahs</hi> time, giving at the Paſſeover, an offering of two thouſand ſix hundred ſmall Cattle, and three hundred Oxen, when notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe were the men <hi>who like Lyons and Wolves tore the people in peeces, and gnawed the very bones, after they had done with the fleſh</hi> (as <hi>Zephaniah</hi> hath told us) <hi>making them as bare and poor as ever they could.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64705:18"/>2 <hi>Herein conſisted a main ground of their hypocriſy and deceiving of themſelves, and ſo of their ruine.</hi> A man muſt wink very hard that doth not ſee the duties of juſtice and mercifulneſſe, of pitty and favourable dealing, &amp;c. writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in capital letters, both upon his own heart, and in the book of God; and one would not think it poſſible that a man ſhould have ſuch ſtrange arts of abuſing himſelf, as to make himſelf beleeve hee is a good man, and in a ſafe condition, while hee violates all theſe known princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>There muſt bee ſome notable blind, ſome very plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble trick, that can caſt ſuch a miſt before his eyes, and jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle him into ſuch a conceited beleef, which here (I think) wee have diſcovered. They had high thoughts of their divine worſhip, and looked upon their religious ſervices as hugely pleaſing to God, and they knew themſelves to be very real, it is like, in this peece of reformation, and ſo they thought themſelves Gods people, the right worſhip being reſtored, the altar of God being cleanſed, and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple repaired by their means.</p>
            <p>Now their great zeal in theſe matters, and their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe to introduce the true Religion, made them overlook theſe little trifling things of juſtice and equity; of mercy and compaſſion; and to hope that God would do ſo alſo, and not bee angry with ſuch a reformed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. What? will not God give leave to a people that hate Idols, and obſerve diligently his Sabbaths, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him his conſtant ſacrifices in the right preſcribed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to bee a little unjuſt, and to get what they can by any arts for themſelves in the world? cannot hee bee pleaſed that they give him his due, and defraud him of none of his right, though they bee not ſo exact in their juſtice one to another? Muſt hee needs take notice what they do among themſelves, when they hope hee hath no reaſon to complain, that he is in any peece of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip neglected?</p>
            <p>Will it not ſatisfye him that they are ſo zealous in thoſe great and weighty concernments of his, which had
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64705:19"/>
been ſo long diſ-regarded, and for which they had been ſo often threatned? Yes ſurely thought they, wee are in a ſafe condition, God is well apayed, wee need not trouble our ſelves any further, but confidently wait upon him, that hee will bee with us and ſave us. Thus the Prophet <hi>tells us, they found a way to deceive themſelves,</hi> as you may read, Mic. 3.11. <hi>The heads thereof judge for reward, and the Prieſts thereof teach for hire, and the Prophets thereof di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine for money:</hi> yet will they lean upon the Lord, and ſay, <hi>is not the Lord among us? none evil can come upon us?</hi> They would needs be Gods favourites, and thruſt themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and bee confident of his goodneſſe to them, though they were conſcious of all this wickedneſs. They cryed the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, as long as thoſe of <hi>Epheſus</hi> cryed, great is <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi> and in this Temple-worſhip and religion they truſted (<hi>Jer.</hi> 7.4.) thinking that God was fixed to that place, and that the Temple would ſecure them, as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the <hi>Trojans</hi> thought themſelves out of all danger, while they could keep their <hi>Palladium.</hi> They dreamt that as long they kept their holy place pure, they need not fear the taking of their City; Juſt as the Heathens thought their fortreſſes could never bee won, while they could keep the good Genius of the place from being charmed away from it. They came and ſtood before God in his houſe, and ſaid, <hi>Wee are delivered,</hi> and that made them do all thoſe fore-mentioned abominations, with the greater boldneſſe, verſ, 10. Yea, knowing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to bee zealous in their worſhip, they have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to come and challenge God as though they had wrong done them, and had hard meaſure at his hands in not being ſaved by him from their enemies; <hi>Wherefore have wee faſted ſay they, and thou ſeeſt not? &amp;c,</hi> Iſa. 58.2, 3. <hi>do wee not ſeek thee daily? do we not delight to know thy waies, and take pleaſure in approaching to thee? why then doſt thou take no knowledge of us?</hi> This, this was the very thing that immediately ruined them; this was it that would not let them ſee the miſchief that was comming upon them for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64705:19"/>
their oppreſſion, violence, and ſuch like ſins. They held faſt this deceit, and ſo refuſed to return, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.5. This made them interpret all the inſtances of Gods diſpleaſure againſt others, to the incouragement of themſelves in their wickedneſſe, rather than to the awakning of their hearts, to repentance. <hi>Ahaz, the Predeceſſor of their good King Hezekiah, was delivered into the hand of the King of Syria, who ſmote him, and carried a great multitude captive unto Damaſcus, and into the hand of the King of Iſrael, who ſmote him with a great ſlaughter, deſtroying an hundred and twenty thouſand valiant men in one day, and carrying cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive two hundred thouſand, men, women, and children</hi> (which indeed were afterwards returned to ſee if they would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend) 2 Chron. 28.4, 5, 8. <hi>The Edomites alſo, and the Philiſtims came and laid them waſte, and brought them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low; The King of Aſſyria likewiſe, who was hired to releeve him, did but more diſtreſſe, and not at all ſtrengthen him,</hi> v. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p>But they could eaſily impute all this miſchief which befell their fathers, unto their Idolatry, <hi>their offering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to other gods, and forſaking the God of their fathers,</hi> verſ. 25. As for themſelves they were returned to him, and hated the ſtrange worſhip with all their hearts, and therefore could bee in no ſuch peril of being deſtroyed; now they amended thoſe very faults, for which their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were ſcourged. This juſtice, and righteouſneſſe were but the vertues of the Heathen, that was round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them.</p>
            <p>The pure worſhip of God was that which diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed them from all others, and would ſecure them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any of that admired Pagan morality.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>Iſrael afterwards is carried captive in the dayes of Hezekiah by the King of Aſſyria,</hi> 2 King 17. But the anſwer was ready, <hi>they worſhipped the calves in Bethel, the remnant of them laughed the meſſengers of Hezekiah to ſcorn, and mocked them who were ſent to invite them to joyn in the Reformation</hi> (2 Chron. 30.6. &amp;c.) <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God cast them out of their land, and continued their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64705:20"/>
captivity;</hi> but how any ſuch evil ſhould betide thoſe that were the reformed, they could not tell how to imagine; no, they were (as the Prophet <hi>Zeph.</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.11.) <hi>haughty, becauſe of his holy mountain,</hi> they bragged of Gods preſence with them, and of the care they had to keep his houſe clean from all heatheniſh impurities; and by this means flattered themſelves into ſuch a conceit of their acceptance with God, and ſecurity under him, that even after the captivity of <hi>Judah;</hi> thoſe in the land of <hi>Babylon</hi> would not bee perſwaded that any more was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to the pleaſing of God, or that there was any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe of their expulſion, but the prophaning of Gods worſhip; let the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> bee called in again to bear witneſſe unto this, <hi>chap.</hi> 33.31, 32, 33. <hi>They came and ſate before him, as though they took a great deal of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in hearing Gods word, when as their heart run after their covetouſneſſe;</hi> which words, by the whole ſtory, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to bee ſpoken to them of the firſt captivity; yea, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the taking of the City the ſecond time, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>And can you think that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were not helped forward alſo to their ruine by this deceit? No queſtion, but they thought their religion, as bad as it was, would preſerve them, and were ſo confident of it, that with the very ſpoil of the poor they would ſerve their gods, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.6.8. <hi>They ſold the righteous for ſilver, and the poor for a pair of ſhooes, they were very corrupt in judgement, and they lay down upon cloaths which they had in pledge by every altar, and they drank the Wine of the condemned in the houſe of their God;</hi> i. e. they ſerved God with thoſe things which they had ſo unjuſtly and violently gotten, and could bee content to ſpend ſomething upon him, ſo hee would but wink at theſe unlawful cruel waies of getting. This iniquity would, it is like, have ſtared them in the face, had it not been for this fine deceit, this Hypocriſy which I ſpeak of, that their ſerving of God, and keeping up his worſhip (ſuch as it was) would bee accepted of God in ſtead of all things elſe wherein they might be faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64705:20"/>And how farre this peece of ſelf-couſenage prevailed in after times, when the Phariſees were in their greateſt height; I leave to thoſe to judge, who read but thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, of <hi>their making long prayers, faſting twice a week, ſtrict obſervance of the Sabbath, and boaſting of God,</hi> while they were the moſt groſſe tranſgreſſours of the Law, and diſhonourers of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Obſerve that this Hypocriſy and partial dealing was cheriſhed by the generality of the Prophets and Prieſts, who were exceedingly corrupted, and cared for no more, but that the worſhip of God might bee maintained, that it might main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them; that there were a multitude of offerings and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, whereby their fees might bee the more plentiful.</hi> They would ſay any thing to pleaſe their rulers, to get their favour, or avert their diſpleaſure, and would preach ſmooth things, that ſhould never grate upon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, leſt they ſhould loſe their gain, or diminiſh their worldly advantages, and would make them beleeve they were religious and godly enough, though they did all thoſe abominations which I have been ſpeaking of: in <hi>Micah</hi> 3.5. the Prophet ſaith, <hi>that they made Gods people to erre, and when any one had put any thing into their mouthes, then they would cry Peace, but if they put nothing into them, then againſt that man they would at an adventure proclaim warre;</hi> hee muſt bee Gods enemy that was not a friend to their belly and purſe; and God could do him no harm, who would bee kinde to them. Unto which adde what is ſaid, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. of the ſame <hi>chapter,</hi> and what the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> charges upon them, <hi>chap.</hi> 22.25, 28, 29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who tells us there <hi>of the defection which both Prieſts, Prophets, Princes and people had made from God; ſo that there was not ſo much as a man to make up the hedge, and to ſtand in the gap againſt the wrath of God, which had made a breach upon them, and particularly of the Prophets and Prieſts, that they were like ravening Lions, had devoured ſouls, made many widdows, daubed with untempered Morter, ſeen vanity and divined lies.</hi> Let mee intreat you to read the whole thirteenth <hi>chapter,</hi> where hee tells us how the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64705:21"/>
Prophets and Propheteſſes <hi>ſeduced the people, preaching peace, when there was no peace, and ſtrengthening the hands of the wicked, that hee ſhould not return from his wicked way, by promiſing him life. Jeremiah</hi> alſo, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.13. Lets us know that even <hi>they were guilty of ſhedding the blood of the juſt, and loved, it ſhould ſeem, oppreſſion and cruelty, as much as the reſt of the Nation.</hi> They cryed up, it is like, the purity of their Church, the holineſſe of their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the devotion of their rulers, and the forwardneſſe of the people to divine worſhip, and concluded, that God could not deſtroy ſuch a people as they were, and that the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould not come into their City; even unto thoſe that deſpiſed the Lord, they ſaid, <hi>you ſhall have peace, and unto every one that walked after the imagination of his own heart, no evil ſhall come upon you,</hi> Jer. 23.17. <hi>Every one from the least, even unto the greateſt, was given unto covetouſneſſe, from the Prophet, even unto the Prieſt, every one dealt falſely, for they healed the Daughter of Gods people ſleightly, ſaying peace, when there was no peace. Were they at all aſhamed, when they had committed all theſe abominations, no, they were not at all aſhamed, neither could they bluſh,</hi> Jer. 8.10, 11, 12. And what was the reaſon of this confidence, but that they thought their Temple-worſhip made amends for all, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>wee are wiſe, ſay they, and the Law of the Lord is with us;</hi> which whether they bee the words of the Prophets, or the people, do ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie that they laid the greateſt weight of their hopes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that peace of Religion which reſpects God, though they had no reſpect at all in their actions towards one another.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not make bold to detain you any longer upon theſe obſerveables, but leaving them to your private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. I come to the ſecond thing to bee briefly illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, which is this, that</p>
            <p n="2">2 Theſe were the very ſins which the Prophets note this people to have been guilty of, after they were returned out of their captivity, and when any one would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected an amendment. Very devout they were, for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64705:21"/>
ought that wee can read; no complaints are brought in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, for not keeping the Sabbath, not praying, faſting, offering ſacrifice, &amp;c. nay, they knew themſelves punctual enough in theſe things, and ſo ſlided into the ſame deceit, wherein their Fathers were caught and periſhed. For in the very beginning of this Prophecie of <hi>Zachariah,</hi> hee cries out, <hi>turn you, turn you unto mee, ſaith the Lord, bee not as your Fathers, unto whom the former Prophets cried the very ſame words,</hi> chap. 1. verſ. 2.3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this was when the captivity was expired, that hee made this proclamation unto them, who as the 5. <hi>chap.</hi> 2.3. teaches us, were ſtill guilty of robbery and perjury with ſuch like ſins, and yet they ſaid they were innocent, ſo <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremel.</hi> read thoſe words, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. <hi>This is the curſe that goeth forth over the face of the whole earth, for every one that ſteals of this people, ſaith as it, (i. e. as the reſt of the earth) that hee is innocent; and whoſoever ſweareth of this people,</hi> as it, ſaith that hee is innocent; they were no more ſenſible of theſe ſins, than Heathen people, who knew but little of God, and might more eaſily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what was only taught them by themſelves.</p>
            <p>And therefore hee goes on to threaten them for ſuch wickedneſſe, and ſpeaking of the woman, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. which ſate in the midſt of the Ephah, by whom was ſhadowed that people, hee ſaith, <hi>this is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> wickedneſſe, iniquity it ſelf, the Mother of all deceit, theft, and perjuries.</hi> And afterward moſt plainly, <hi>chap.</hi> 8. having told them how the caſe ſtood with their Fathers, <hi>hee tells them that now hee was returned to Zion, verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>and that hee would bleſſe them now, as hee had curſed them before, verſ.</hi> 13. but then hee ſaith, <hi>theſe are the things that they must do. Speak yee every man the truth, execute the judgement of truth and peace, &amp;c. verſ.</hi> 16, 17.</p>
            <p>If wee look back to <hi>Haggai,</hi> who prophecied but two years before theſe words, in the 8. <hi>Zach.</hi> were ſpoken, (one being in the ſecond, the other in the fourth year of <hi>Darius</hi>) hee will tell us no better newes of this people, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>every thing that they did was as bad as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64705:22"/>
thoſe illegal offerings, and impure ſacrifices;</hi> and hee ſeems to intimate that they had not <hi>with a holy minde, compoſed to all obedience, hitherto offered ſacrifice to God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee could not accept them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I think if wee compare this paſſage with what wee before gathered out of <hi>Zachary</hi> (who as I ſaid was his contemporary) wee ſhall eaſily diſcern what the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was that God was offended at in their doings.</p>
            <p>At the firſt they neglected the worſhip of God, and let the Temple lie waſte, building their own houſes before it; and when they were awakened by theſe Prophets to that work, then they thought that all was well, and that there needed no care of any other thing, ſo the building of the Temple were but carried on unto perfection; and thereupon continued in a world of wickedneſſe, making their zeal for Temple-work, eat up all their love to juſtice and mercy.</p>
            <p>If wee ſhould trace their foot-ſteps further, wee ſhould ſoon finde, that when the Temple was compleated and finiſhed, they were but little better. For <hi>Malachy</hi> (who is called by them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſeal of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, becauſe hee was the laſt, and ſhuts up all) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the iniquity both of Prieſt and people, ſets down theſe ſins as famous among the reſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.5. <hi>falſe ſwearing, oppreſſion of the hireling in his wages, of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and fatherleſſe, and turning aſide the ſtranger from his right;</hi> which together with other ſins made way for that long captivity which indures to this day, as thoſe acquaint us, upon whom the ſpirit of Propheſy was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain poured forth. For Chriſt comming and reproving the chief of them, <hi>for devouring widdows houſes, for extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, rapine and blood, for covetouſneſſe and oppreſſion, while they made long prayers, and pretended a great deal of ſanctity and religion; he declaring alſo that faith, judgement, mercy, and the love of God were more to bee regarded, than their ſtrict obſervance of daies and ſacrifices, &amp;c.</hi> They out of a great zeal for their religion, which they thought hee did not ſpeak honourably enough concerning, moſt ſhamefully
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64705:22"/>
put him to death. And I beleeve they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very religious perſons, and were ſerious in what they did, only their great and unequally diſpenſed zeal, for theſe few things, made them beleeve themſelves ſo good, as not to ſee themſelves ſinners while they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all manner of wickedneſs, and eaſily to ſlide into the uſual Hypocriſy, <hi>i. e.</hi> partiality in obedience.</p>
            <p>Their great zeal for thoſe things made them take themſelves for pious and devout perſons, but the partiality and particularity of it, made them really to be ſuch as our Saviour calls Hypocrites, which appellation they took in ſuch diſdain, that they conſpired his death, who would not let ſuch as they paſſe for godly men.</p>
            <p>I ſhould be too tedious, ſhould I proſecute this through all the ſtory. This truth ſhines clear enough without bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing any more light from other Scriptures, that theſe have been often the waſting and deſtroying ſins, becauſe commonly not obſerved in the midſt of a blaze of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duties, which dazle mens eyes, and make theſe ſins ſeem either none at all, or very little and contemptible; which leads mee unto the third thing which I am to make proof of.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>That theſe are ſins which pull down ruine, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon a Nation, and indeed are oft the chiefeſt cauſe of it.</hi> The Poet never ſpoke truer word, than when hee ſaid,<note place="margin">Pindar.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (that is as the Scholiaſt well notes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) there is ſcarce ſuch a tall and impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable bulwark, ſuch a ſafe defence to a Nation as juſtice; and then I am ſure it is like to bee laid waſte, when there is a breach made in this wall, for oppreſſion, violence and wrong to enter in, which I have as good as already clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, while I have brought in the Prophets every where cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out upon theſe ſins, as the cauſe of their deſolation, and being carried captive out of their own land.</p>
            <p>But if you deſire more particular ſatisfaction, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That the captivity of Iſrael is in a great part charged upon the account of theſe ſins,</hi> and take the pains to conſult
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64705:23"/>
but theſe two places in a Prophet, whoſe viſion was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ten Tribes, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. <hi>Amos</hi> 4.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>The captivity of Judah, both firſt and laſt is moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly aſcribed to them</hi> (theſe being the iniquities which even in their reformations they ſpared from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed) and I muſt again put you to the pains of conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe places (which the time will not give mee leave to inlarge upon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.12, 13, 14. <hi>Micah</hi> 3.12. and eſpecially that remarkable one, <hi>Jer.</hi> 34. where hee calls upon them <hi>to let the Bondmen of the Hebrew Nation go free, according to the Law,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe after their promiſe they refuſed, and kept them ſtill in their ſervice; ſee what is threatned, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18, 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to this that paſſage (I am apt to think) relates, which wee meet withall in the very beginning of <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> Lamentations <hi>Judah is gone into captivity, becauſe of affliction, and becauſe of great ſervitude, chap.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Babylon her ſelf who deſtroyed Judah, was deſtroyed for theſe ſins</hi> (which I note, leſt you ſhould think that theſe things concerned only that particular people, and do not bode ſo ſadly to other Nations, where they are found) in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.5, 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7, it is ſaid that God ſent the Aſſyrian <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Hypocritical Nation that I have been deſcribing, and gave him charge to take the ſpoil, &amp;c.</hi> but hee thought of nothing but deſtroying and cutting off Nations; and therefore hee threatens <hi>to deſtroy him utterly, and to take off his burdens and yoaks from his people, verſ,</hi> 26, 27. and more fully, <hi>chap.</hi> 14.3, 4, 5, 6. hee notes <hi>the hard bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage wherewith they made the conquered ſerve, and their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and ruling the Nations in anger, as cauſes of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> To which may bee added that moſt evident place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.5, 6. where plainly hee ſaith, that <hi>cruelty and oppreſſion toward thoſe whom ſhee had overcome, brought the Lady and Miſtreſſe of the World down to ſit in the duſt in perpetual ſilence and darkneſſe.</hi> And take notice that one reaſon why this miſchief was not prevented, and this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction came upon them while they thought not of it,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64705:23"/>
was the ſame with that which wee met withal in the caſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> viz. <hi>The baſe flattering humor of their ſooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, the men-pleaſing prophecyes of her diviners, and thoſe watchmen they had</hi> (though pittiful ones they were) <hi>who had told them lyes, juſt as the watchmen of Gods people, had to them,</hi> which the latter part of that chapter doth give us reaſon to take for a truth.</p>
            <p>I will refer you but to one place more, which moſt largely treats of the Chaldeans ruine, <hi>Habak.</hi> 2. from the fifth verſe to the eighteen, which whoſoever reads muſt caſt his eyes very careleſly upon it, who doth not ſee that <hi>unſatiable covetouſneſſe, cruelty, bloudineſſe, violence, ſpoiling, aad ſuch like ſinnes;</hi> are made to have a greater hand than their idols, <hi>in reaching the cup of the Lords right hand unto them, and making them ſo drunken, and full gorged, that ſhameful ſpuing ſhould bee upon all their glory</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How long ſhould I detain you, if I ſhould multiply more particulars from <hi>Nineveh, Nahum.</hi> 3.1. from <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus, Gaza, Edom, Ammon,</hi> and all the reſt mentioned in the firſt and ſecond Chapters of <hi>Amos,</hi> who were all threatned for their oppreſſion and cruelty, to bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed without any mercy.</p>
            <p>I will onely deſire you to conſider as you read thoſe chapters, whether you can refuſe to aſſent to this as a true obſervation, that one great deſtroying (if not the chiefeſt) ſin of thoſe people there mentioned was this, <hi>their unmercifulneſſe and cruel dealing with thoſe whom they had conquered, and got into their power;</hi> I am ſure that <hi>Edoms</hi> four tranſgreſſions are ſo neer of kin to this, that wee can ſcarce make them any more then four degrees of this one ſin, viz. <hi>want of kindneſſe, compaſſion, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to thoſe whom it was natural for him to pitty,</hi> eſpecially when hee had the better of them, verſ. 11. <hi>Hee did pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue his brother with the ſword, and did caſt off all pitty, and his anger did tear perpetually, and kept his wrath for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64705:24"/>And I think there is another whole Chapter which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders no other cauſe of the periſhing of thoſe <hi>Ammonites, Moabites, Edomites,</hi> and <hi>Philiſtims</hi> alſo, but this, <hi>that they either rejoyced and clapped their hands at the ruine of their Neighbour Judah, or elſe with an implacable, and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcilable hatred, proſecuted their victories over them, intending their total deletion and final deſtruction. Ezek.</hi> 25. But as I ſaid, I will not now make ſo bold as to prolong this diſcourſe, till a particular narrative bee given you of all theſe things. Nor will I do any more than ſuggeſt to your meditation that <hi>Ammon is again threatned, for inſulting upon the necks of the ſlain,</hi> i. e. <hi>of a faln and feeble enemy,</hi> Ez. 21.29. v. Jun. and <hi>Pharoah</hi> for deceiving and cozening the expectation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who leaned upon his promiſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29.6, 7. And the Iſraelites themſelves <hi>for ſlaying their brethren of Judah, with a rage that reached up to heaven, and without any pitty, intending to make them bondmen,</hi> 2 Chron. 28.9, 10. <hi>and that in general it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced that the robbery of the wicked ſhall deſtroy them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they refuſe to do judgement, &amp;c.</hi> Prov. 21.7, 15. and that <hi>God hath ſtiled himſelf the avenger of the poor, and needy, and hee that will plead the cauſe of thoſe that have no helper, that are cruſhed by the mighty, and cannot right themſelves, nor have any other to do them right;</hi> and that theſe are ſuch unnatural ſins, and ſo contrary to all the dealings of God with men (who is merciful, kinde, and compaſſionate, as well as juſt and righteous) that God will not let them go unpuniſhed, eſpecially in the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, whoſe office it is to ſee right, equity, and mercy, take place among men.</p>
            <p>The Jews you have ſeen are a notable example of this, and by often experience, it ſeems they were ſo ſenſible of it, that there grew to bee a common ſaying, among their wiſemen of this ſignification, <hi>That when Gods ears are ſhut againſt all mens prayers, he will hear the cry of the poor, needy, and oppreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quando vaſtata fuit domus ſanctuarii, omnes porta clauſa fuerunt (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) excepta porta oppreſſionis, i. e.</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:64705:24"/>
when the Temple was deſtroyed, there was no gate open for the Prayers and Petitions of any to enter, but onely <hi>the gate for the Petitions of the oppreſſed,</hi> which they ſay is never ſhut.</p>
            <p>This they prove (as <hi>Buxtorfius</hi> hath noted) out of the 7th of <hi>Amos</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>And hee ſhowed, and behold the Lord ſtood upon the wall made by a Plumb-line; the words in the Original are</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which they interpret; <hi>upon the wall of defraudation or oppreſſion; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and in his hand were defraudations, i. e.</hi> Prayers againſt Defrauders, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of thoſe who complained of Oppreſſion and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt dealing (of which wee have heard enough to have been in thoſe times.) Even in <hi>Iſraell</hi> (if this interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee true,) where they had faln from God, hee would not exclude the ſuites of ſuch perſons, but take their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt into his hands, and let them have a favourable au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. See <hi>Eccleſi.</hi> 21.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35. <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am not much concerned to diſpute the truth of this Gloſſe, ſeeing the thing which it aſſerts, is already put out of all doubt; and this very Prophet preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaith, that <hi>theſe are ſuch works as God cannot forget to puniſh, Amos</hi> 8.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. and there is ſuch particular no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice taken of the <hi>ſhedding innocent bloud,</hi> 1 King. 24.3, 4. <hi>as an iniquity that hee will not pardon.</hi> And therefore leaving it to obtain what credit it can get with thoſe who are skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in that language, I ſhall deſcend to the fourth and laſt thing, which I am engaged to treat of.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>That where peace, ſetlement and ſafety it expected by men, they are to have a great care to ſee whether they bee guilty of ſuch things as theſe, and if they bee, deeply to bee humbled, and ſpeedily to reform.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe ſhould bee the more minded upon ſuch a day as this, becauſe as you have heard all along, many have cozened themſelves by the willing performance of ſome religious dutys, into a moſt dangerous ſecurity, and vain confidence in God, while by reaſon of theſe ſins (which are counted by ſuch perſons but ſmall petty matters, in compariſon with their glittering piety) they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64705:25"/>
have been working their own ruine.</p>
            <p>Theſe things were propoſed to the people before their captivity, as matters to bee reformed, if they hoped for any favour from God; as we may ſee in <hi>Amos</hi> his words to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had been much waſted and ſpoiled (chap. 4.) from the ſeventh verſe of the fifth chapter to the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth verſe, and again repeated with abundance of ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Do not make a noiſe in my ears with good words and flattering devotions, away with thoſe offerings, and ſacrifices, in which you are ſo forward, but let me ſee judgement and righteouſneſſe like a mighty torrent carry all before it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To whom conſents the Prophets <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> concerning <hi>Judah;</hi> as you ſhall inſtantly underſtand? if you will bee at no more labour but to caſt your eyes upon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14, 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 58.8, 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c. Jer.</hi> 7.5, 6, 7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.2, 3, 4, 5. which very thing they might have learnt from the experience of their fathers, v. 15, 16, 17. <hi>who judged the cauſe of the poor, &amp;c. and was not this to know mee ſaith the Lord?</hi> Yes, This is the buſineſſe, though you would fain make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve you know mee, while you are Covetous, Unjuſt, Bloudy, Cruel, and unmerciful, &amp;c. and would perſwade your ſelves, that you are a Religious People, and ſhall bee in ſafety, yet there is no ſuch matter, do not deceive your ſelves, it went well with your fathers onely when they did judgement and juſtice, and then they truely had the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p>And therfore when they are returned from <hi>Babylons</hi> ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, this is the means propoſed to them for a ſettlement here preſently after my Text, v. 9, 10. this is the buſineſſe of ſuch a faſting day, as will turn away Gods wrath. The Jews ſay, that <hi>merces jejunii eſt eleemoſyna,</hi> the beſt thing in a faſt is an act of mercy, and there is ſome truth in the ſaying, <hi>for the righteous Lord loveth righteouſneſſe, his countenance doth behold the upright, and with the merciful, he will ſhew himſelf merciful. The inſtruments of the churh are evil, hee deviſeth wicked deviſes to deſtroy the poor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64705:25"/>
with lying words, even when the needy ſpeaketh right, but the liberal deviſeth liberal things, and by liberal things ſhall hee ſtand,</hi> Pſal. 11.7, 18, 25. Iſa. 32.7, 8. <hi>And when judgement ſhall dwell in the Wilderneſſe, and righteouſneſſe remains in the fruitful field, then we finde it follow, that the work of righteouſneſſe ſhall bee peace, and the effect of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe quietneſſe, and aſſurance for ever, and that his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in ſure dwellings, and in a quiet reſting place,</hi> as wee read in the ſame 32. of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Two words of caution to prevent all miſtakes, ſhall ſhut up this diſcourſe, becauſe I ſee that I ſhould beyond all reaſon try your patience, if I ſhould adventure to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſo much of this as belongs to our caſe, unto your hearts, and that I ſhould too much ſuſpect your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if I ſhould go about to tell you how to improve eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Then bee pleaſed to take notice that <hi>I do not take upon mee to bee as one of thoſe Prophets, nor to ſay that our Nation is guilty of all theſe ſins, and that our caſe is exactly paralel to that of the Jewiſh people.</hi> I onely lay it down as a true poſition, that this was the condition of that people, and this the cauſe of their ruine, and that upon ſuppoſition, that the ſame things are found amongſt any other, in all likelyhood they will bring down the ſame venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>All the Application I make to our own ſelves of theſe things is, that every man (would all both one and other in the Nation were told ſo much) ought to enter into his own heart, and to conſider whether there bee any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in his hands, any of the bloud of the poor and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed running about his fingers, while hee lifts up his hands to God, any unjuſt acquiſitions that he is conſcious to himſelf of, &amp;c. if theſe things bee not found amongſt us, wee may have good hope that God will not make us a deſolation, but if they bee, wee ought deeply to bee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled this day for our hypocritical faſting and humiliation, that while wee have mourned and prayed, <hi>and would
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64705:26"/>
needs lean upon God, and cry the Temple of the Lord, and called for the building up of Syon;</hi> wee have not minded ſo much as matters of <hi>common juſtice, equity and mercy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a man and his neighbour,</hi> and wee may fear that the Lord will make <hi>an utter end of us, unleſſe we do ſpeedily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our wayes and doings. For the Hypocrital Nation is the people of Gods wrath, and hee will bee avenged of ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.6 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.24</note> 
               <hi>and eaſe himſelf of his adverſaries. When hee goes into his vineyard,</hi> Iſa. 5.7. <hi>and looks for judgement, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold oppreſſion, for righteouſneſſe, but behold a cry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> when men are grown to that condition, that they hope theſe matters of Juſtice are but a trifling buſineſſe, and that the change of ſo ſmall a thing as a Letter, the placing of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the ſtead of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the room of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> will make no great change in Gods affection to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and bee accounted but a petty overſight; Then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately comes out a woe in the following verſe, and an aſſeveration, <hi>that many houſes ſhall bee deſolate, even great and fair without an inhabitant,</hi> verſ. 8, 9. and v. 20. unto 25.</p>
            <p>If I may bee allowed to ſay any more, it ſhould bee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, that the Rulers of the People ought carefully and impartially to inquire into themſelves about theſe matters, they being more than others concerned in them (as many of theſe places which I have alledged will tell him that reads them) and having greater power and temptations to do theſe things than moſt of the people, or at leaſt to come nearer in their ſins to the height of Prophetical expreſſions than the ordinary ſort of men, in regard of whom thoſe phraſes muſt bee interpreted with ſome diminution and abatement.</p>
            <p>I am ſure they every where note it, as a ſad thing when <hi>the rulers cauſe the people to erre,</hi> but I ſhall mention now onely that ſingle place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.14, 15, 16, 17. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that I am now ſpeaking in an auditory where there are no Rulers that have fearce power to do any body any wrong, but are far I am perſwaded from having any will.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:64705:26"/>If any one have occaſion to treat of theſe matters in a more publick Aſſembly, it might not perhaps bee intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable in him to propoſe this Queſtion, whether wee may not fear (though I have excluded all confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent aſſertion as to my own particular) that if a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſhould now riſe up in the Chriſtian (yea in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) world, hee would thunder out againſt it, that men make little difference of <hi>fas and nefas,</hi> right and wrong, that they invade one anothers rights and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, wallow in bloud and cruelty, &amp;c. and yet cry up the purity of Religion; the merits of Chriſt Jeſus and ſuch like things, with as loud a voice as they in the Prophet did, <hi>the Temple of the Lord,</hi> yea, whether it bee out of all doubt; that hee would not have any better lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for thoſe who are double refined from Popery, and have reformed even the reformation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>I do not ſay that theſe are the onely ſins that undo a people, nor that ſins more immediately againſt God, as denying of his being, and his truths, and blaſpheming of his name, &amp;c.</hi> (if they bee general) <hi>are not waſting ſins, nor that theſe are the more hainous in themſelves than thoſe against God.</hi> All that I affirm, is, that theſe alone are (and have been) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to deſtroy a Nation without the other, and that theſe commonly prove the moſt dangerous, and ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a Nation of any elſe, becauſe they are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overlooked (whereas one would think the duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our brother whom wee ſee ſhould bee moſt eaſily in our eye) and when men reform impieties againſt God, they think themſelves to have done him ſuch high ſervice, and are ſo much in thoſe upper ſpeculations, that they take no notice of theſe things under their feet, and make no reckoning how they deal with men, ſo they bee but zealous and fierce for that which is due to God; or they can bee content to bee religious, ſo they but retain their unlawful gains, pleaſures and ambitious ends; yea, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps their religion and forwardneſſe for reformation in other things, may give them a better advantage, more colourably to practice theſe iniquities, and their unmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64705:27"/>
affections, will eaſily put them in minde to make uſe of ſuch opportunities.</p>
            <p>Religious ſervices in their greateſt outward puritie, beſides that the natures of men are not ſo averſe unto, and abhorrent from them, but that they may bee very forward to do them; they alſo make a great ſound and din in the world, and have ſuch a glorious appearance, that by the doing of them hee may bee reputed, and alſo take himſelf for a Saint, and then bee ſo pleaſed with this fine perſwaſion, and ſo inwardly tickled with the delight of ſuch thoughts, that hee is ingaged to minde with all his power the promoting of ſuch matters as have gained him the credit of a holy perſon, without denying his worldly luſts, which may rather have a freer liberty under ſuch a brave and ſplendid maſter, as ſtands not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on punctilio's of honeſty and equity between one man and another. But if wee turn our eyes the other way, wee ſhall finde, that <hi>juſtice and mercy, pitty and compaſſion, forgiveneſſe and doing of good to others</hi> (eſpecially to thoſe who have wronged us) will fall out ſometimes with a mans worldly intereſts, and carnal deſires, and will put him to learn that hard leſſon of ſelf-denyal; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide they make no ſuch great noiſe in the world, but muſt bee content to paſſe with many men, for a peece of dull morality.</p>
            <p>It was moſt truly ſaid by a very wiſe man, <hi>Nulli fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius ad magnam pietatis famam perveniunt, quam ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſi &amp; hypocrytae.</hi> They that have nothing elſe to ſhew for their ſanctity, but their religious performances, will bee moſt nice, exact, and even ceremonious about them, and do them with a greater pang of zeal, than many cordial Chriſtians, which eaſily obtains for them the name of holy and devout perſons among men, when honeſty, mercy, and a ſober religion and piety cannot prevail for ſo much credit. Whence is it that men are eaſily tempted to neglect theſe things while they minde the other, and ſo the ſins of injuſtice, &amp;c as I have been proving, oftner undo a Nation, than any other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:64705:27"/>Hence I ſay again, it is that theſe things do more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ruine a Nation, than corruption in Gods worſhip; not becauſe that is not deſtructive, but becauſe men will a great deal ſooner reform the one than the other; a fair outward correſpondence in all the outward worſhip of God, being a great deal more eaſy, than this denial of mens ſelves in their covetous, malitious, ambitious and other fleſhly deſires; and being apt to get a man a higher name, if it bee in any good meaſure of fervency and heat, and likewiſe to beget in himſelf a comfortable opinion that hee is truly pious. And ſeeing there is ſuch Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy and deceit in mens hearts, and they are ſo willing thus to cheat themſelves; I hope it will not bee deemed unſeaſonable that I have treated of this matter, rather than the other.</p>
            <p>It is obſerved you know by ſome, that no men can ſo ſecurely commit all wicked actions, as they who have gained the repute of honeſt men; and therefore the Poet in <hi>Plutarch</hi> moſt cunningly adviſeth,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">De aud. Poetis.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Do all thou canſt to bee accounted juſt, and ſpare to do nothing whereby thou mayeſt bee a gainer. But then, what may not, what will not he do that hath ſecured, not only other mens opinion, but his own alſo, of his honeſty and piety. This is a farre worſe couſenage, than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for a man to deceive himſelf, as well as other folks, and will moſt inevitably bring him to ruine.</p>
            <p>If it bee a great peece of that policy whereby the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil rules the world, for a man ſo notably to counterfeit piety, that even when hee doth moſt deſtroy it, hee ſhall bee counted pious, (as it was ſaid of <hi>Tereus</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>— Ipſo ſceleris molimine Tereus</l>
                  <l>Creditur eſſe pius. —</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:64705:28"/>Hee was cryed up for a Saint, even when hee was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the greateſt villany) What a notable peece of the Devils craft, then is it ſo to perſwade a zealous man in religious duties, and ſo to inflame him, that he ſhall paſſe in his own judgement for a Saint? How certainly will he ruine both himſelf and others? in what a ready way is hee to commit all injuſtice, when hee is out of all danger of having his own conſcience ſecretly reprove him of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy and ſimulation, which the other had not ſo ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? When a man makes a conſcience of ſome things, and is very forward in them, they make ſuch a noiſe, that they quite drown the voice of it in other matters, and with the greater ſafety, hee commits all other kinde of wickedneſſe, which are no leſſe dangerous, than that which hee avoids.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not treſpaſſe upon you much further. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this bee aſſented unto which I have now diſcourſed, or not, this notwithſtanding will remain good, that ſuch ſins are a cauſe ſufficient of a peoples ruine, though there bee no other, and therefore for the Lords, our own, and the Lands ſake, let us not look upon theſe things as leſſer and inconſiderable, which need not bee ſo much preſſed upon mens practiſe, nor the Pulpits ſo much ſound of, leſt by this means the Prieſt and the people ſhould both periſh together.</p>
            <p>Let the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> bee once more allowed to ſpeak, and I will preſently conclude, <hi>chap.</hi> 30.8, 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c. Note it in a book, that it may bee for the time to come, for ever and ever; that this is a rebellious people, lying chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, children that will not hear the Law of the Lord, which ſay to the ſeers, ſee not, and to the Prophets, prophecie not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us right things: speak unto us ſmooth things, prophecie deceits, get yee out of the way; turn aſide out of the path; cauſe the holy one of Iſrael to ceaſe from before us, &amp;c.</hi> They would not have the Prophets ſpeak to them of things that were right and honeſt, but deſired ſome ſoft; ſleek, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and deceitful doctrins (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64705:28"/>
abuſe them) that they ſhould cry <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Kimchi</hi> there notes) <hi>do according to your hearts deſire, and it ſhall bee well with you;</hi> they would not have them run in the old beaten way, and preach ſo much ſtrictneſſe of righteouſneſſe unto them; no, <hi>finde ſome new ſmooth path, wherin wee may go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any rub to our own luſts, cauſe the holy one of Iſrael to ceaſe from before us,</hi> i. e. <hi>let us hear nothing of the holy one any more;</hi> preſſe not holineſſe ſo earneſtly and frequently upon us. But what ſaith God to ſuch a people? The 12, 13, &amp; 14. <hi>verſe</hi> will tell us. <hi>Thus ſaith the holy one, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you deſpiſe this word (becauſe you like not to hear of the holy one) and truſt in oppreſſion and perverſeneſſe, and ſtay thereon (hoping that you ſhall fare well enough)</hi> Therefore (mark what the holy one, the righteous God that hates iniquity ſaith) <hi>This iniquity ſhall bee to you as a breach ready to fall, ſwelling out in a high wall, &amp;c.</hi> juſt as a <hi>wall that ſwells, and often burſts on a ſudden, falling down upon thoſe who are under it, that dream of no ſuch thing, and crumbles all into duſt or little bits that can bee put to no uſe at all; ſuch ſhall your ruine bee,</hi> i. e. <hi>totall and inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, becauſe unexpected, and not beleeved through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of your hearts, and your falſe confidences in other things, while you remained guilty of thoſe iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord open every mans eyes, that he may ſee how farre he is concerned in any of theſe truths, that hee may paſſe ſentence upon himſelf, and prevent the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, <hi>who hath ſet his throne for judgement, who will judge the world in Righteouſneſſe, and miniſter judgement to the people in uprightneſſe. His eyes behold, his eye-lids try the children of men. The Lord tryeth the Righteous: but the wicked and him that loveth violence, his ſoul hateth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="quotation">
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Chriſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
